Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. New York Office. Resor Library Records, 1822-1967
The John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
J. Walter Thompson Company. New York Office. Resor Library records 1822-1967
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
J. Walter Thompson Company. New York Office.
4.5 Linear Feet 616 Items
Founded in 1864, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) is one of the largest and oldest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. The Resor Library was a project initiated by Helen Lansdowne Resor to enhance the intellectual and cultural environment in the JWT New York corporate headquarters at the Graybar Building on Lexington Avenue.
The Resor Library Records contain books and book inventories, as well as correspondence, memoranda and invoices related to purchases of books for the JWT Resor Library between 1927-1930. The bulk of the books were published between 1890 and 1919. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Resor Library Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 1987.
Historical Note
In 1927 the New York office of the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) moved from 244 Madison Avenue to the Graybar Building at 420 Lexington Avenue. The event provided Helen Lansdowne Resor an opportunity to create a showcase in JWT's new corporate headquarters. She commissioned Norman Bel Geddes to design a lecture hall and hired numerous interior designers (among them Elsie de Worl) to decorate specific offices. Additionally, she commissioned Samuel Yellin to create iron grill-work for the executive wing and moved an entire Colonial kitchen to serve as a private dining room.
Lansdowne Resor wished to improve not only the visual appeal of the offices but also the intellectual and cultural environment. Therefore she commissioned noted historian Lewis Mumford to compile a list of three thousand books to be purchased for the use of company employees. Mumford was likely chosen because of his views on the study of civilization; Mumford emphasized the importance of the study of the interrelationships between social, economic and artistic events. He applied this approach in particular to the study of America's history and as a result is largely credited with the re-discovery and renewed appreciation of our popular cultural heritage.
Mumford solicited input from a variety of sources: existing book lists; outside experts; employees' recommendations; as well as his own choices. He divided the books into three general categories: Science, Arts, and Ideologies. Sub-categories were included under each general heading.
The project of physically collecting the individual volumes fell to Fanny Bell of the Research Library. Bell was charged to supply the volumes as quickly and cheaply as possible, which Bell began to do in February 1927. In April 1927 she discovered Dauber and Pine Bookshops, a used book dealer on Fifth Avenue. For the next six years, Dauber and Pine was the primary supplier for the library. By 1930 books began to disappear from the collection. The last survey, taken on October 23, 1967 listed 44 remaining titles. Sometime later the collection was dispersed. Materials in this collection comprise all the volumes that remain of the library.
[Notes derived from those written by JWT Archives staff.]
Collection Overview
The Resor Library Records contain books and book inventories, as well as correspondence, memoranda and invoices related to purchases of books for the JWT Resor Library between 1927-1930. The bulk of the books were published between 1890 and 1919.
The collection consists of two series: General Files and Books. The General Files Series contains correspondence, memoranda, invoices, book lists, and inventories related to Resor Library book purchases. The Books Series contains books purchased for and housed in the Resor Library.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
J. Walter Thompson Company
J. Walter Thompson Company. New York Office
Mumford, Lewis, 1895-1990
Resor, Helen Landsdowne, 1886-1964
John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Related Material
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections of the J. Walter Thompson Company Archives:
Colin Dawkins Papers
Norman H. Strouse Papers
Artifacts and Memorabilia
Newsletter Collection
Contents of Collection
- General Files, 1927-1967, (2 boxes)
  Contains correspondence, memoranda, invoices, book lists, and inventories related to the Resor Library. Maintained in the original order received from JWT Archives.
  - Mumford list of original 125, 1927 Apr. 2 (Box 1)
  - Preliminary list, 1927 May 27-June 17
  - First thousand, 1927 June 8, 2 copies, (2 folders)
  - Preliminary list, 1927 June 29
  - Preliminary list, 1927 June
  - Second thousand, 1927 June 17
  - Final list: Dauber and Pine copy, 1927 Oct., (4 folders)
  - Final list: company copy, 1928 Sept., (4 folders)
  - Correspondence, memoranda and invoices regarding dealers other than Dauber and Pine, 1927-1929, (3 folders)
  - Correspondence, memoranda and invoices regarding Dauber and Pine, 1927-1928, (8 folders)
  - Correspondence, memoranda and invoices regarding Dauber and Pine, 1929-1935, (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and memoranda regarding Lewis Mumford, 1927-1930, (4 folders)
  - Correspondence and memoranda regarding progress on Resor Library, 1927-1930
  - Lists of missing books, 1930-1942
  - Inventory of books, 1966-1967
- Books, 1822-1928, (8 boxes)
  Contains books purchased for the Resor Library at the recommendation of Lewis Mumford. Organized alphabetically by title.
  - Binyon, Laurence. Painting in the Far East: An Introduction to the History of Pictorial Art in Asia Especially China and Japan, Second edition. New York: Longmans, Green & Co.; London: Edward Arnold, 1913 (Box 3)
  - Birrell, Augustine. Obiter Dicta. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1893 (Box 4)
  - Buckle, Henry Thomas. History of Civilization in England, vols. I-II. London: John W. Parker & Son, 1857
  - Butler, Samuel. Hudibras: A Poem, vols. I-II. London: Ackerman, Strand, 1822
  - Carlyle, Thomas. Frederick the Great, vol. I. London: Chapman and Hall,1858-1865
  - Carlyle, Thomas. Frederick the Great, vols. II-V. London: Chapman and Hall, 1862-1865 (Box 5)
  - Carlyle, Thomas. Frederick the Great, vol. VI. London: Chapman and Hall, 1862-1865 (Box 6)
  - Cervantes Saavedra, Miguel de. Don Quixote, vol. I. Translated by Henry Edward Watts. New York: D. Appleton & Co., 1898
  - Compayre, Gabriel. Abelard and the Origin and Early History of Universities. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1893 (Box 7)
  - Croce, Benedetto. European Literature in the Nineteenth Century. Translated by Douglas Ainslie. New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1924
  - Cushing, Frank Hamilton. Zuni Folk Tales. New York: G.P. Putnam's Sons, 1902
  - Farrand, Livingston. Basis of American History: 1500-1900, vol. 2 of American Nation: A History. Edited by Albert Bushnell Hart. New York: Harper & Bros., 1904
  - Faure, Elie. Ancient Art, vol. 1 of History of Art. Translated by Walter Pach. New York: Harper & Bros., 1921
  - Hamilton, Alexander, James Madison and John Jay. The Federalist, vol. I. Washington, D.C., M. Walter Dunne, 1901
  - Holroyd, Charles. Michael Angelo Buonarroti. London: Duckworth and Co., 1911 (Box 8)
  - Homer, Iliad of Homer. Translated by Alexander Pope. New York: D. Appleton & Co., 1899
  - Pater, Walter. The Renaissance. New York: MacMillian and Co., 1901 (Box 9)
  - Ruskin, John. Fors Clavigera: Letters, vols. I-IV. London: George Allen, Sunnyside, Orpington, 1896
  - Ruskin, John. Sesame and Lilies. London: George Allen, Sunnyside, Orpington, 1898
  - Ruskin, John. Seven Lamps of Architecture. London: George Allen, Sunnyside, Orpington, 1898
  - Ruskin, John. Stones of Venice, vols. II and III. London: George Allen, Sunnyside, Orpington, 1898 (Box 10)
  - Smollett, Tobias. The Expedition of Humphry Clinker. London: George Routledge and Sons., Ltd., 1895
  - Thackeray, William Makepeace. Irish Sketch Book. London: Smith, Elder & Co.; Philadelphia: J.B. Lippincott & Co., 1886
  - Thackeray, William Makepeace. Lovell the Widower. London: Smith, Elder & Co.; Philadelphia: J.B. Lippincott & Co., 1886
  - Whitehead, A.N. Organization of Thought, Educational and Scientific. Philadelphia: J.B. Lippincott Co., 1917